ALBERT GARRETA

I am a mathematician and computer scientist (PhD). I began my career conducting research on algorithmic problems in algebra and discrete optimization. Later I became interested in other areas such as machine learning (particularly reinforcement learning), and in cryptography and blockchain technology.

CONTACT



- Pilbao, Spain
- homepage
- Github

 Google scholar profile

 Kaggle profile

KEYWORDS

- Algorithmic problems in rings, groups, etc.
- Machine learning
- Cryptography
- Blockchain technology and development

PROGRAMMING SKILLS

Python
Solidity
Rust
C++
LaTeX

LANGUAGES

English
Spanish
Catalan

ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS

m 07/2021 - today

▼ BCAM Basque Center of Applied Mathematics, Bilbao (Spain)

in)

1 01/2017 - 07/2021

♥ University of the Basque Country, Bilbao (Spain) Postdoctoral Researcher

Postdoctoral Researcher

EDUCATION

1 08/2012 - 12/2016

Stevens Institute of Technology,
New Jersey (USA)

PhD in Mathematics

Received an excellence in graduate research award

1 09/2007 - 07/2012

Polytechnic University of Catalonia, Barcelona (Spain) Licenciature in Mathematics

Roughly equivalent to what currently is a 4-year college degree and a 1-year master's degree

SELECTED WORK AND ACHIEVEMENTS

 Publication of mathematical and computer science papers at top ranked journals.

E.g. in Bulletin of Mathematical Sciencies, **ranked 17 out of 325** in the category of Mathematics (JCR criterion).

9th out of 1089 solution to the machine learning competition Photometric LSST Astronomical Time-series Classification Challenge (PLASTICC) (Kaggle).

Co-authorship of the paper describing the 10 best solutions to the competition, set to appear at the *The Astrophysical Journal Supplement*, with rank **7th out of 68** in the category of Astronomy and Astrophysics (JCR criterion)

Teaching and theses direction for the Master's degree Blockchain Technology and Crypto-Economy (link in Spanish).

GENERAL SKILLS

Commutative and non-commutative algebra Group and semigroup theory Number theory Discrete optimization Computational complexity Algorithms Cryptography Group-based cryptography Machine learning Deep leaning Reinforcement learning Statistical inference Blockchain technology and developmeny Python Solidity Rust LaTeX Research presentation and divulgation Self-learning Art **Painting**

13. A decentralized private data marketplace using blockchain and secure multi-party computation with Julen Bernabé and Oscar Lage	
	% preprint
12. Group equations with abelian predicates with Laura Ciobanu	% preprint
11. Solving word equations with Monte Carlo Tree Search and black-box solvers Albert Garreta 2021 Submitted for revision	% preprint
10. Diophantine problems in rings and algebras: undecidability and reductions to rings of a	
with Alexei Miasnikov and Denis Ovchinnikov 2021 Submitted for revision	% arXiv
9. Results of the Photometric LSST Astronomical Time-series Classification Challenge (PLAsTiCC) with Renee Hlozek et al.	
	% preprint
8. Simple groups with infinite verbal width and the same positive theory as free groups with Montserrat Casals-Ruiz, Ilya Kazachkov, and Javier de la Nuez 2021 to appear in Israel Journal of Mathematics	% arXiv
7. On equations and first-order theory of one-relator monoids with Robert D. Gray 2021 Information & Computation, vol. 281, 104745, ISSN 0890-5401, 44 pages	% doi, arXiv
6. On the positive theory of groups acting on trees with Montserrat Casals-Ruiz, and Javier de la Nuez	- 1%(8 doi, arXiv
5. Metabelian groups: full-rank presentations, randomness and Diophantine problems with Leire Legarreta, Alexei Miasnikov, and Denis Ovchinnikov	
ii 2021 I Journal of Group Theory, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 453-466	% doi, arXiv
 4. Diophantine problems in solvable groups with Alexei Miasnikov and Denis Ovchinnikov ■ Bulletin of Mathematical Sciences, v. 10 (1) (2020), pp. 1-21 	% doi, arXiv
3. Full rank presentations and nilpotent groups: structure, Diophantine problem, and gene with Alexei Miasnikov and Denis Ovchinnikov	% doi, arXiv
2. Engel elements in some fractal groups with Gustavo Fernández-Alcober and Marialaura Noce	
## 2018 ■ Journal of Group Theory, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 453-466	% doi, arXiv
1. Random nilpotent groups, polycyclic presentations, and Diophantine problems with Alexei Miasnikov and Denis Ovchinnikov	
≅ 2017 ■ Groups Complexity Cryptology, v. 9 (2) (2017), pp. 99-115	% doi, arXiv

Regressing bone age from radiographs via interpretable features with Jordi Fortuny, Oscar Gasulla, Ferran Mazaira, and Miguel Teixidó

Regressing bone age from radiographs via interpretable features with Jordi Fortuny, Oscar Gasulla, Ferran Mazaira, and Miguel Teixidó

Studying the Diophantine problem in finitely generated rings via bilinear maps with Alexei Miasnikov and Denis Ovchinnikov

Equations in polycyclic groups with Alexei Miasnikov and Denis Ovchinnikov

MACHINE LEARNING COMPETITIONS

THESES SUPERVISED

SMPC & BLOCKCHAIN: Creating Private Data Marketplaces Julen Bernabé (supervised by Albert Garreta and Oscar Lage)

% link

Blockchain Homomorphic Encryption

Leire Etxebarria (supervised by Albert Garreta and Oscar Lage)

≜ 2021 **►** Blockchain Technology and Crypto-economy (Master's Degree)

% link

TEACHING

Modern Cryptography

Blockchain Technology and Crypto-economy (Master's Degree)

Foundations of Cryptography

Blockchain Technology and Crypto-economy (Master's Degree)

Modern Cryptography

Blockchain Technology and Crypto-economy (Master's Degree)

Foundations of Cryptography

Blockchain Technology and Crypto-economy (Master's Degree)

Introduction to Deep Learning

5h PhD Course

Data Science and python programming

Bachelor of Business Administration

Differential Equations, Multivariable Calculus

Several undergraduate courses (around 500 hours in total)

2012-2016

♀ Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, (New Jersey, USA)

INVITED TALKS AT CONFERENCES

CONTRIBUTED TALKS AT CONFERENCES

ACADEMIC VISITS

AWARDS AND GRANTS

ORGANIZATION OF CONFERENCES AND SEMINARS